<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on AlexAndSchaefer</title>
    <link>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on AlexAndSchaefer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Alexander Schaefer</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Recommendations - Hands-on Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow</title>
      <link>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/handson/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/handson/</guid>
      <description>This is the first post in a series. Where I want to highlight my all time favorite books. These are technical books that helped me throughout my studies and career. Most of them are very easy to read and translate a lot of knowledge to you very quickly.
I start here with Hands-On Machine Learning by Aurélien Géron. This book actually made me want to start this series. As I really want to recommend this book to anyone interested in the topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Customer Behavior - A General Approach</title>
      <link>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/predictingcustomerbehaviour/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/predictingcustomerbehaviour/</guid>
      <description>In my work as a data scientist at Project A. I often encounter the task of predicting customer behavior. For many businesses it can be very valuable to estimate which one of their new customers will be the most profitable in the future. Or which one of the existing customers will stop being valuable. In this context many tasks such as predicting churn, customer lifetime value or ending of newsletter subscription are of interest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Feature Encoding</title>
      <link>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/featureencoding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://AlexAndSchaefer.github.io/post/featureencoding/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I wanted to make a blog post on prediction problems I encounter in my work as data scientist at project-a. While working on the post I realized that feature encoding might be too basic for some readers; while very much needed for others. As a consequence I decided feature encoding should become its own post.
What is feature encoding? Not all information we have at hand is suited for the machine learning algorithm we want to use.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>